This entire phase of duodenal development is a phase of rotation,
it is an organizing phase for the duodenal framework, small intestine, and
colon.
And now we will see it in the context of the colonic framework in relation to the duodenum.
You see me in profile; I have my aorta, and we will read like this,
in depth, regarding the colonic framework,
that I have a spiral movement, the duodenum, the small intestine, and
the colon.
whose driving force for organization will be the liver.
If I look at this depth, we will see that it develops
into what we call an organized facial pentagon
around the pancreas.
Do you remember the retro-cavity of the omenta?
I have the right layer of the visceral peritoneum at the level of
my stomach
that forms this small fold.
And immediately, by the development of my liver, it goes backward and
creates a dynamic where the stomach positions itself,
where the right side becomes posterior and the left side becomes anterior.
And it creates this space.
At the same time, I have a whole development of my intestine that begins to occur.
For the duodenum, which will mainly involve a 90-degree rotation from the left
to the right,
it is an axis of rotation for the hepato-pancreatic organization.
gastric and linear. Initially, it is straight, it is a tube that organizes itself a bit in
movement
like this, with the upper intestine, the middle intestine, and the lower intestine. But in this phase
of rotation, when it does this, imagine what happens here, you need to envision this as a growth,
but it creates spaces of torsional movement like that, of intra-tissue rotation.
And these
phases of rotation will create a whole area we call sphincters.
Thus, all of these sphincters will be created in this dynamic phase of development.
It creates joints.
A joint, for example, the sphincter between the stomach and the duodenum is called
the pyloric sphincter.
And we will see that the pyloric sphincter responds to the positioning between the development
to the right of my liver
and the gastric movement to the left on its axis of rotation, with the tissue
developing inside there.
will be called the lesser omentum.
This means that the lesser omentum, at the edge of my stomach and at the hepatic level,
when we take a lesser omentum, it is the tissue that organizes and rebalances
the pyloric sphincter.
We will begin to reflect on this dynamic regarding the power of development.
The overall movement, the organization, of all this development will create what we call
sphincter functions.
At the same time, I also have my two pancreatic
buds, one
ventral; I remind you that it
comes like a gland, like the lungs,
it's the same principle, like the liver.
Ultimately, the liver is just an expansion
of a digestive tube on an
endodermic plane. I have the
pancreas, the anterior layer
and the posterior layer
that will undergo this phase of
rotation,
which will follow this phase of rotation. The pancreas
will develop
in this movement as well.
This framework of the deep development at the level of the peritoneum is
just a movement developed between my stomach, my
liver, and the colonic framework that will organize these sphincter functions.
The setup movement determines the function of the sphincters.
So it means that here you have the pyloric sphincter created by the movement of the liver
and the stomach.
This is an important point for the entire rotation.
The definitive rotary rotation of 270 degrees of the colonic framework,
while the sphincter of Di is the definitive result
of the rotation of the common bile duct and the pancreatic-biliary complex.
It's also a very important sphincter.
If you look at this setup,
there is this pancreatic movement and this movement of the common bile duct.
So that means releasing a sphincter of Di
in its embryonic fulcrum is releasing the facial pentagon.
Pancreas and releasing the liver. This is where I will have my two support points. This point here, c
is a
large reflex area for enzymatic, hormonal, biliary, and neurovegetative regulation. For example,
at the hormonal
level, there is a parathyroid relationship with calcium receptors. Here,
it corresponds to the setup between the liver and the stomach. The
sphincter of Di is a balance
between a developmental fulcrum of my pancreas,
in its phase of rotation and of my liver, at the biliary level,
while the sphincter, this time the duodenal,
is created by the setup of the small intestine,
which is a joint between the duodenocolic system
in relation to the mesenteric system.
At this level, the information can be modified
by gastroileal information, by coloileal information
or by...
cologastric information. This little point here is one of the areas that will modify the
deep influence
of all digestive vascularization. Since here I have a small magic muscle that we call
the muscle of Tretz that can lift or relax, thus reducing
the information coming from below
or upstream and decreasing regarding the celiac trunk the information of a gastro
-gastric.
or linear or hepatic.
So it means that this information, depending on whether it is hypocaloric or hypercaloric,
for example from a food bolus, can completely change your vascular behavior in
a digestive state.
So you see how this point becomes a reflex point,
becomes a super important point and is just a joint
between the small intestine in its phase of rotation which develops
on a plane where it first integrates into the anterior integrity and then towards the posterior part,
where I will have here all the root of the mesentery that
links the duodenum to the colon.
So what happens here can be an imbalance here.
But on that, at the level of my colon, concerning my diaphragmatic system,
I have the suspensory ligament at the angle between...
the third and fourth duodenum, which can open or close the information and thus
therefore
reduce the vascular space.
We have another sphincter that will develop, the ileocecal sphincter.
It is related to the definitive setup of all the frameworks between the mesentery
and
the descent of the definitive framework of the right colic angle.
If I want to work on a pylorus in a child, there is a way to position it.
If I want to work on an immune system in a child, I will
be immune in a child, there will be a way to position it.
The brain just needs to have knowledge of movement
and the system will do it by itself.
You just give it its fulcrum,
that is, the very nature of the system can express itself freely.
The anal sphincter will be related on the axis of the inferior mesenteric artery.
All the left information is linked to the inferior mesenteric artery,
while all the right information is linked to the superior mesenteric artery.
Two trophic movements, organizing all the space,
but centered at the level of the duodenum.
Because at the level of the duodenum, you have duodenal pits
that can, depending on the whole, close or increase your system.
For example, a sigmoiditis in relation to a duodenal pit
that is fixed on a purely ileocecal plane.
Each sphincter has at least two main functions.
Both a mechanical function, to change the purely.
enzymatic, hormonal, neurovegetative or otherwise,
and also a function of type information, of type neurovascular.
It will open or close a facial environment.
The muscular plan of the duodenum is a plan that has a splanchnic pattern
through the common mesodermic pathway, at the diaphragmatic level,
through the suspensory ligament of the pleural dome,
at the aortic level, via the celiac trunk and all this global information,
via the esophageal system.
adrenal. I have in this framework a concentration of information, a
bit like at my
phenobasilar symphysis, on an anatomical and physiological analogy level. I
can place the
base of the skull in a pentagon, Crista galli, the
greater wings of the sphenoid, the petrous system,
the occiput, etc. And the base of the skull which is here, the same thing here, I find it in
a kind of pentagon, and the body builds.
constructed in a pentagon. This will be another work on the analogical forces. To treat
for example an arm will release information on a facial plane that will be found on
a purely gastric or renal or adrenal level or a great wing of the sphenoid.
I will
show you the almost synchronous link between, for example, the falx cerebri and
the ligament
falciform or between the primary and secondary root at the sigmoid level that
will be
at a purely occipital petrous level or at a level in
the left upper limb because
it is just an expansion of a system. The duodenum, the liver, does not exist. It is an
environment; it is a swirling energy with phases
where you just need to lean.
It is just a tube with an environment, but spatially and geometrically organized.
And this geometry allows us to understand analogies because
You saw, at one point, in the little film, we saw this here, movements like this.
But in fact, we can also study what happens like this.
What will develop there, you will see that it develops at the same time.
We will take a common pattern which will be the development of the brain.
This means that, from the facial articulation of this duodenum,
it will ultimately determine a digestive state of metabolic type.
If I have a meal, it will determine this digestive state.
It will also determine...
A vegetative state, which means that a destabilization of your
duodenal frame, because it moves, can for example give a neurovegetative dystonia,
a depressive state.
To treat depression, one must release a duodenal frame, one must raise
the intestine, and one must redynamize the system just on a facial plane.
This will restore energy on a deep level, regarding the microbiotic flora.
which is a huge genetic heritage,
which informs through their production and their enzymatic change,
on a genetic level, the brain plan in its primary function.
It is a relationship with my ganglia, with my sympathetic system, parasympathetic,
with my system of semilunar ganglia, right, left, mesenteric plexus.
Both it is facial, but as it is filled with informers and receptors,
they will also function with serotonin plans.
80% of serotonin, after all, comes from the intestine, these are ascending fibers.
The duodenal plan is one of the most informed on the autocrine, paracrine, and neurocrine levels.
Everything in the second duodenum, in relation to the sphincter of 10, which is filled with
glycocalyx.
These are simply information receptors of digestive type
or otherwise.
When your food arrives, it’s like this at the caloric level.
Pancreas, you release this, liver, you go get that, you will stir a bit more.
go get gastrin, we need to increase
our hydrochloric acids to restore
pure energy. The duodenum,
is a concentrated place for that.
On a metabolic level, this compression
can lead to malabsorption
of certain proteins,
like sugar proteins,
lactose and lipids,
if you will find, vitamin D,
A. Vitamin D is very
important for calcium absorption that occurs
at the level of the D sphincter.
This means that osteoporosis can also have
a purely digestive aspect due to malabsorption regarding the
reports of
hormonal information between the parathyroid and calcium receptors from the
duodenum concerning calcium information. This means that on this hormonal level it is
also ultimately a rebalancing of the acid-base system that will be
reflected this time on a neurovegetative level on the hypothalamic level
that will give you an organizational chemistry that will thus affect
the organization of your sphincters
On a postural level, it concerns the acid-base postural chemistry organized by your duodenum
on a hypothalamic level and reorganized in your ergatropic system, paratropic.
If I move my pelvis like this, I open a sphincter, I
close a sphincter.
If I position myself like this, I close here, I open over there.
It’s all an organization in your body that will play to increase or decrease
the passage of information.
I will find in my posture.
a typology of constipatory type or of diarrheal type.
So I will simply modify my quality of information transfer,
but even on a molecular level.
So it means that osteoporosis has an origin that can be digestive,
related to an acid-base imbalance at the gastro-duodenal level,
since this is the site of resorption at the membranous level that will take place at this level,
at the cellular level, which is determined by gastrin,
which is determined by the...
at the level of the third duodenum and which is also linked to the secretion of thyrocalcitonin.
So the 2D sphincter is a balance on a fulcrum between the rotary movement of my pancreas
and the developmental movement of my biliary system.
This 2D sphincter on an embryonic plane in its developmental phase
is related to the development of my liver and
my pancreas.
The first fixed point that will develop at this level
will be the left colic angle.
Then there will be another fixed point that will be formed internally,
and the most mobile point will be the right colic angle, the cecum.
On a chronological plane, first,
one of the first small movements will be this hepatic movement.
So the main motor, the main fulcrum, will be the liver.
So releasing the motility of the liver,
redynamizing the liver,
is to restore a global support point for the system.
Look at the concentration on a vascular, arterial, venous,
renal,
knowing that I also have the relationship with the stomach, with the liver, with my pancreas,
with my small intestine, and thus directly with my colon, with my transverse system.
The anatomical structure here is very important and we will see it in detail.
A destabilization of the duodenal framework can be a destabilization...
of your fertility. Because you have here an artery that passes, which is the
spermatic artery,
the ovarian artery, which provides all the atrophicity. You have another level
which is the superior mesenteric artery, and then you also have the inferior mesenteric artery.
This destabilization can completely destabilize in depth
the dynamic, hemodynamic flow. And we will see that one of the masters of
this relationship
will be the muscle of Tretz.
For the moment, what you retain is that there is a relationship with the lesser omentum
which will form my first sphincter, the lesser omentum which is the tissue
of articulation
between the liver and the stomach that will form the pyloric sphincter.
You have a second very important sphincter which is a 2D sphincter in relation to the
pancreas and the liver, support point of the biliary channels or
pancreatic channels with this
enzymatic point.
hormonal point. Another important sphincter here, duodenojejunal sphincter, in
relation to the
diaphragm via the muscle of Tretz, in relation to the colonic system via
my mesentery, relationship
duodenal-jejunal and colonic. So what happens here can
express itself there and thus influence
for example an imbalance at the immunity level since this is an immune level, it is a
concentration of lymphoid tissues.
that function synchronously on a fluidic level
given by the information from bacteria.
The importance of epithelial cells is the glycocalyx in the duodenum,
filled with receptors.
The duodenum must be viewed with its environment tissue.
It is its peritoneum.
Between the transverse mesocolon, here, which is there,
and the mesoduodenum, you have small pits
called the supra
the infraduodenal pit, the duodenojejunal pit,
which are what? In fact, places for passage of arterial level.
This peritoneum, these are double blades carrying vessels.
An excessive stress will give me at the level of the retro-cavity of the omenta,
a viscero-spasm, I will decrease the possibility
of irrigation.
These duodenal pits are thus arteriovenous pits.
Naturally related to my kidneys, related to the superior mesenteric veins
inferior mesenteric veins,
the inferior mesenteric vein is deep.
Imagine a pancreatic problem or a viscero-spasm, I have my pancreas, I
have something that tightens in my stomach,
whether it is psychological, whether it is digestive, or whether it is something else, I decrease the irrigation,
that means it will determine a metabolic and digestive state.
ultimately at the sigmoid level.
Sigmoid colics, sigmoid polyps,
ulcerative colitis,
all this is related not only to the semilunar ganglia,
thus the sympathetic, parasympathetic system,
and related to the diaphragmatic pillars.
Treating a sigmoiditis or ulcerative colitis
that may supposedly originate...
purely psychologically may find its origin in the depth of your duodenal framework.
And that releasing this vascular field is re-releasing the atrophicity.
The same goes for the right; if I have a destabilization, I have a loss of irrigation.
So I have a problem of poor irrigation at the testicular, spermatic level
or at the ovarian level.
What happens at the periphery may perhaps find an origin in a simple viscero-spasm
between plane A.
and the duodenal plane to bring back energy,
re-release the deep frame to recover your serotonin,
recover your transmitters.
This will also re-release the adrenal glands.
The adrenals are really important little hats
with a peripheral part and a central part
whose all specific adrenergic neurotransmitters, etc.,
come from the inner part of your adrenals
and are very important for the system.
for the proper functioning system of your neurotransmitters, cortisol,
which can inhibit your thyroid or inhibit your pituitary factors
simply due to poor adaptation to stress, for example.
This shows us that the duodenum is informed by the mobility of the kidneys,
which is informed by the mobility of your liver.
The Glisson's capsule can destabilize your entire lymphatic drainage axis.
We know that the perirenal fascia, thus at the level...
of this psoas bed
drains up to 1 liter
to 1.5 liters of lymph per day.
So that means it is your entire waste disposal system
that must balance
look at this muscle of Tretz
it is really a continuity of the diaphragm
it is one of the most important
crossroads
on the vascular plan of your digestive system
it's my celiac trunk
I have the whole system
hepatic, gastric
Linel, what departs from there?
I rise, I do a viscero-spasm, I change the vascular state
here.
It is made of two parts, a muscular part and a fibrous part.
So, two types of different information.
I will have a direct relationship with the phrenic nerve,
which is in relation to the phrenic center, thus with my cervical column,
therefore with C3, C4, directly here, through muscular, reflex.
How can this give shoulder pain or cervical pain?
By releasing this zone there, you will immediately release your cervical rotation.
It's normal since it's a reflection pathway.
Do not forget that it works like this.
These viscero-spasms can reverberate via sensory fibers in the system.
And in fact, instead of going back into that, they return on lateral motor pathways.
I have my C3, I have my C4.
Not only do I have a phrenic nerve, but I have a remote relationship.
ganglia where I will return to other systems, including irrigation or
innervation
at the cervical level or at the simply level of your arm or your elbow. This is a
neurological path
but also a fascial path since it is an expansion of your cardiopleuro
-peritoneal sac.
If I pull or if I close, I increase or decrease the duodenojejunal angle.
So I can have a
reflex state at the cecal level, through the mesenteric pathway.
with a lymphatic pathway, lymphatic, lymphatic, mesenteric,
and then I find myself on ergatropic or trophotropic plans
through the concentration of ganglia of the parasympathetic or sympathetic type.
With my aorta, which will be found in rotation phases,
I can destabilize my heart by an aortic movement here.
So I can release an aorta here to release a branch here,
and thus release a whole information here.
You see that it is a support point in its part.
This is where we will release it, this is where we will rebalance it.
What surrounds it? The esophagus.
What surrounds it? The celiac trunk.
And there, what do I have? Superior mesenteric.
So the whole arcade here and a bit lower, what do I have? All the inferior mesenteric.
Do you understand a bit the idea of this power, of this facial pentagon?
I take all my fascias and I do like this.
I get into the thing, and now I pull, I have everything, and there I
am attached.
And what he said, all your colon, all your peritoneum,
all your intestines are attached to the aorta and to the spine.
vertebra.
The muscle of Tretz informs about blood flow, at the intra-peritoneal level
and at the supramesocolic level.
The muscle of Tretz is informed by all the frameworks, through a plan.
metabolic and by a mechanical plan and above all do not forget its relationship
with the kidney, the psoas
which can for example give us gonalgia. It will be necessary to reconcentrate the
peritoneum in its
origin fulcrum and also at its terminal point. Not only does it have its
fulcrum but it also has its
arrival point. This is about its pure electric concentration on a magnetic level. On
an
energetic level there is a subtle energy circulating.
Because we can place this in a pentagon like this.
You have an important point here.
Ileocecal, hepatic, gastric, colonic
left, very important support point, sigmoid.
Then I enter into the small star, here, here, here, here, here.
Here are the key points of a peritoneal work.
And this lesser omentum, it is the one we will learn to clear.
I have at the same time a hepatic blade that picks up the portal vein, the artery
and the biliary pathways.
So I have a very important level, purely metabolic, of digestive type
and circulatory.
Well, my lesser omentum, it’s there.
And like this, we will go from the right side, here.
There, I have the pure vascular hepatic blade.
I find myself with the portal vein.
The portal vein.
here I have my hepatic duct and here I have the proper hepatic artery
and all this
is maintained, held in the lesser omentum
so not only do I have a very important embryonic support point but not only do I have a freedom point for all my return
metabolic of venous type here I have all this sigmoid side that comes here and
there I have
this cecal side that returns here.
And here, I have all the relationship
with my second duodenum
on this bile duct.
All this is enclosed in a fascia.
Together, I am maintained
with one part later which is
a rather free edge and an edge
more condensed after, which picks up
the complete meso of the right layer,
the left layer of my gastric plan.
There, I take the stomach.
And between my two,
portal veins, arteries, and legs.
biliary duct here there I have a softer edge and
then behind here I have a
more free edge, there I am on a support point and there I will simply go
into an overall state little by little returning this freedom of tissue from
the surface and there I really have the axis of rotation between my liver and
my
stomach so I have all the future organization of my retro-cavity of the
omentum
and of all the primitive duodenal rotation.
So this first portion of the duodenum,
we can say it is related to the lesser omentum.
The posterior part of the layer is continuous with the hepatic vein.
So it is the duct of the portal vein
and which determines the flow of return
and therefore all the rebalancing of sigmoid or
colonic stasis.
It is also fixed by the muscle of Tretz,
neuroduodenal, hepatic stability, diaphragmatic stability.
The second duodenum is related to the hepatocystic-colonic system,
that is to say with also my ureter and the duodenum.
So it is important to treat the kidneys, to release the perirenal fascia,
to release the psoas when treating a duodenum.
The third duodenum will mainly relate to the lumbar system
middle, L3-L4.
with all the relationship at the ovarian artery level and the testicular artery.
So all fertility problems, I have all my relationships concerning
my second duodenum,
there, with my diaphragm, and which has a diaphragmatic lemniscus.
I have a lemniscus here, through this play here, and then I have a great lemniscus
on my pelvic plane,
which relates to a large lemniscus.
of Winslow, it's the entrance to the retro-cavity of the omenta.
You see this movement, you who do this, when I leave, I enter, that is the hiatus of
Winslow, then I enter into the vestibule, I go in behind, and then I have my
walk.
The path of osteopathic knowledge, it is always important to study embryology
which will help you understand anatomy, anatomy will help you understand physiology, physiology,
will lead you to a study of pathophysiology, and then you will understand
that in pathophysiology.
that has a link with psychology.
Psychology will lead you to philosophy,
and philosophy will lead you to spirituality.
This means that you will be able to release your deep attachment plan
to dare to find your emptiness.
You do this with each breath.
You return your breath each time.
If you really give back, you can die in peace.
Ultimately, all the work is to die in peace.
That is why meditation is a training of death every moment.